Jackson College for Women Records UA033
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Jackson College for Women Records
1910 -- 1985
1871 -- 1985
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Miller, Russell E.
Jackson College
UA033
10.75 Linear Feet 12 boxes
1 Artifact(s)
55 Digital Object(s)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.The collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Jackson College records; and Unprocessed accessions.
Biographical / Historical
Named after Cornelia Maria Jackson, who bequeathed funds to Tufts to help "remove the disabilities of women," Jackson College was founded in 1910 as a coordinate college to Tufts. An alternative to both women's colleges and fully coeducational schools, coordinate colleges provided women with a separate, and supposedly equal, education at a women's college that existed in conjunction with a men's school.
Women were first admitted to Tufts College in 1892, some forty years after the college's founding, and their presence was a continual source of debate among the faculty, administration, and Trustees. As an alternative to coeducation, President Frederick Hamilton, himself an opponent of coeducation, argued for the establishment of a separate, coordinate college. This compromise resulted in the establishment of Jackson College. Caroline Davies, the first woman to serve on the Tufts faculty, and the first female administrative officer, was named as the first dean.
Segregated instruction lasted only a few years, and by the time the catalogue for 1913 was published all mention of separate classes for women was gone. From 1917 to 1963 women graduates received Tufts degrees only. From 1963 until 2002, women's diplomas carried an identification of Jackson College.
Socially, however, the concept of Jackson College remained strong until the 1970s. Jackson College had its own student government, clubs, and other student organizations. The Jumbo, the undergraduate college yearbook revived in 1917, had separate sections for Tufts College and Jackson College through the 1960s.
Although no longer a separate part of the university, Jackson College is still a legal entity and the title of the undergraduate division of the university remains the College of Liberal Arts and Jackson College.
Custodial History
The collection contains material gathered by Russell Miller in preparation for writing his two volume history of Tufts, "Light on the Hill." Some photographs have been removed to the University Image collection, but there are several boxes of photographs that are grouped at the end of the collection.
Related Materials
UA039, Classes Collection, DCA
Scope and Contents
This collection is sharply focused on student activities specific to Jackson College including records of the student government and social groups and activities. There are also three scrapbooks of the Jackson College Athletic Association, which include clippings and photographs of athletic events.
Also included in this collection is material related to women at Tufts prior to the establishment of Jackson College in 1910.
Student Activities -- Student Government, Clubs, and Organizations; Student Activities -- Athletics; Student Activities -- Performing Arts; Student life; Student activism; Alumni and Alumni Relations
- Jackson College, records, 1871 -- 1985; UA033.001; 7.15 Linear Feet; 1 Artifact(s); 55 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains material gathered by Russell Miller in preparation for writing his two volume history of Tufts, "Light on the Hill." The material is sharply focused on student activities specific to Jackson College including records of the student government and social groups and activities. Some photographs have been removed to the University Image collection, but there are several boxes of photographs that are grouped at the end of the collection.
  Arrangement
  This collection is arranged by subject.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - All Around Club Alumnae Production, 1913; UA033.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Alumnae Material, 1960 -- 1978; UA033.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Association for Women Students' Self-Government, 1905; UA033.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Association, 1906 -- 1965; UA033.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Association, 1903 -- 1911; UA033.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Association, 1952 -- 1953; UA033.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Class Dramatic Productions, 1924; UA033.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - College Bowl, 1967; UA033.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - College Equal Suffrage League, 1904; UA033.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Continuing Education, 1969 -- 1973; UA033.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, office of the dean, 1927 -- 1970; UA033.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Father/Daughter Weekend, 1960 -- 1961; UA033.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate Dramatic Association Minutes, 1928; UA033.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Masque Society, 1917 -- 1930; UA033.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    The Masque of Jackson College playbill for "Children of the Moon" gift of Alfred H. Fuchs, 2019, accession UA-2019-063.
  - Masque Society Minutes, 1925 -- 1930; UA033.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - New England Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools Membership, 1943; UA033.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1960 -- 1968; UA033.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Parent's Weekend, 1954 -- 1958; UA033.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Physical Education Reports, 1929 -- 1941; UA033.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Physical Education Reports, 1942 -- 1948; UA033.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Self-Study Committee, 1967; UA033.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Semi-Centennial, 1960; UA033.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Shakespeare Tercentenary Celebration, 1916; UA033.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Student Government Judiciary Council, 1963 -- 1969; UA033.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Student Government Judiciary Council, 1961 -- 1968; UA033.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Student Council, 1910 -- 1969; UA033.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1926 -- 1927; UA033.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1927 -- 1930; UA033.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1931 -- 1935; UA033.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1939 -- 1942; UA033.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1942 -- 1946; UA033.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1946 -- 1950; UA033.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1950 -- 1954; UA033.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1935 -- 1939; UA033.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1954 -- 1957; UA033.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1957 -- 1961; UA033.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1961 -- 1963; UA033.001.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1963 -- 1964; UA033.001.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - Student Council Minutes, 1965 -- 1969; UA033.001.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Student Government: Elections, 1966 -- 1969; UA033.001.005.00005 (Box 5)
  - Student Government: House Judiciaries, 1962 -- 1969; UA033.001.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - Student Government: Orientation, Honor Code, 1958 -- 1969; UA033.001.005.00007 (Box 5)
  - Student Government: President's Reports (Judiciary), 1961 -- 1963; UA033.001.005.00008 (Box 5)
  - Student Government: TCU, JSGA, 1967 -- 1970; UA033.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
  - Student Statistics, 1954 -- 1969; UA033.001.006.00002 (Box 6)
  - Tufts Alumnae Association Productions, 1924 -- 1925; UA033.001.006.00003 (Box 6)
  - Jackson College photographs, 1912 -- 1925; UA033.001.007.00001 (Box 7)
    - Officers of the Social Service Organization, 1922; UA033.001.007.00001.00001; Unknown (Box 7)
      People; Student activities; Students; Ford, Miriam; Neal, Peggy; Prescott, Louise; Maertins, Gertrud; Campbell, Pete; Jackson College
    - Jackson students on Armistice Day, 1918; UA033.001.007.00001.00002; Unknown (Box 7)
      People; Students; Jackson College
    - Jackson Day, Romeo and Juliet, 1920; UA033.001.007.00001.00003; Unknown (Box 7)
      People; Students; Theater; Jackson College
    - Jackson basketball team, 1920; UA033.001.007.00001.00004; Unknown (Box 7)
      Students; Athletics; Basketball; Jackson College
    - Jackson sorority group, 1912; UA033.001.007.00001.00005; Unknown (Box 7)
      Students; Sororities; People; Jackson College
    - Three Jackson College students, 1925; UA033.001.007.00001.00006; Unknown (Box 7)
  - Jackson College photographs, 1920; UA033.001.007.00002 (Box 7)
    - Jackson track meet, 1920; UA033.001.007.00002.00001 (Box 7)
      Students; People; Athletics; Track (Women's); Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1926 -- 1937; UA033.001.007.00003 (Box 7)
    - Jackson College students in front of Eaton Hall, 1926-05-19; UA033.001.007.00003.00001; Munro, Melville S. (Box 7)
    - Presidents of Jackson College organizations, 1930-10-23; UA033.001.007.00003.00002; Unknown (Box 7)
      From left to right: Elizabeth King '31, Elizabeth Peabody '31, Ruth Libbey '31, Ruth Fedor '31, Dorothea Loughlin '31, Kaye MacKinnon'31.
      People; Student activities; Students; Jackson College
    - Members of Jackson College Kappa Phi, 1935-05-13; UA033.001.007.00003.00003; Unknown (Box 7)
      People; Students; Clubs; Jackson College
    - Jackson Student Council, 1937-05-06; UA033.001.007.00003.00004; Unknown (Box 7)
      Student activities; People; Students; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1935; UA033.001.007.00004 (Box 7)
    - Jackson basketball coach Eleanor Dexter with captain Blanche Downing, 1935; UA033.001.007.00004.00001; Munro, Melville S. (Box 7)
      People; Students; Athletics; Basketball (Women's); photographic print; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1937; UA033.001.007.00005 (Box 7)
    - Three Jackson honors students, 1937-10-15; UA033.001.007.00005.00001; Munro, Melville S. (Box 7)
      From left to right: Jean M. Forsyth, Rits C. Modelia, Iris Kelman.
      People; Students; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson tennis team, 1937-05-17; UA033.001.007.00005.00002; Unknown (Box 7)
      People; Students; Athletics; Tennis (Women's); photographic print; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1938 -- 1939; UA033.001.007.00006 (Box 7)
    - Jackson student government officers, 1939-05-04; UA033.001.007.00006.00001; Munro, Melville S. (Box 7)
      From right to left: Harriet Mehaffy '42, Thiess English '40, Carolyn Baker '41, Ruth Glidden '40.
      People; Student activities; Students; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson class of 1938 senior class officers, UA033.001.007.00006.00002; Munro, Melville S. (Box 7)
      From left to right: Jane Fitzpatrick, Louise Remick, Elizabeth Bancroft, Dorothy Manuel, Lois O'Brien.
  - Jackson College photographs, 1931 -- 1937; UA033.001.007.00007 (Box 7)
    - Three Jackson College golf players, 1937; UA033.001.007.00007.00001; Unknown (Box 7)
      People; Students; Athletics; Golf; photographic print; Jackson College
    - University Club swimming, 1933-03-09; UA033.001.007.00007.00002; Unknown (Box 7)
      People; Women; Swimming; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson orchestra, 1931; UA033.001.007.00007.00003; Unknown (Box 7)
      People; Students; Music; photographic print; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1940 -- 1947; UA033.001.008.00001 (Box 8)
    - Jackson Student Council, 1947; UA033.001.008.00001.00001; Duette Photographers (Box 8)
      People; Student activities; Robes; Students; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Students in radio at Jackson, 1947; UA033.001.008.00001.00002; Unknown (Box 8)
      From left to right: Ruth Halstrand, Virginia Atwater, Betty Dempsy, Letitia Doble.
      People; Students; Radio Stations; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Two Jackson students with unidentified measuring device, 1945; UA033.001.008.00001.00003; Unknown (Box 8)
      Students; People; Laboratories; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Kappa Phi, 1940-05-14; UA033.001.008.00001.00004; Unknown (Box 8)
      Students; People; Clubs; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Sally Elwyn working with inoculating cultures during World War II, 1944; UA033.001.008.00001.00005; Unknown (Box 8)
      People; Laboratories; Women; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Woman golfing on Jackson Day, 1905 -- 1940; UA033.001.008.00001.00006; Frieze, H.R. (Box 8)
      3 1/2 x 4 1/2
      People; Students; Golf; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1947; UA033.001.008.00002 (Box 8)
    - Jackson students sponsor food drive, 1947; UA033.001.008.00002.00001; Unknown (Box 8)
      People; Students; Charities; photographic print; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1940 -- 1949; UA033.001.008.00003 (Box 8)
  - Jackson College photographs, 1950 -- 1959; UA033.001.008.00004 (Box 8)
  - Jackson College photographs, 1950 -- 1959; UA033.001.008.00005 (Box 8)
    - Jackson swimming team, 1955; UA033.001.008.00005.00001; Unknown (Box 8)
      People; Students; Swimming; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Synchronized swimming at Jackson, 1957; UA033.001.008.00005.00002; Unknown (Box 8)
      Students; People; Swimming; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Dean Bush looking at pictures with a student, 1950 -- 1959; UA033.001.008.00005.00003; Duette Photographers (Box 8)
      People; Students; Photographs; photographic print; Bush, Edith L.; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1961; UA033.001.009.00001 (Box 9)
    - Jackson students in dance class, 1961; UA033.001.009.00001.00001; Unknown (Box 9)
      People; Dances and Dancing; Students; Athletics; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Dance class at Jackson, 1961; UA033.001.009.00001.00002; Unknown (Box 9)
      People; Students; Dances and Dancing; Athletics; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson Athletic Association, 1961; UA033.001.009.00001.00003; Unknown (Box 9)
      People; Students; Athletics; photographic print; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1961 -- 1965; UA033.001.009.00002 (Box 9)
    - Jackson students horseback riding, 1961; UA033.001.009.00002.00001; Unknown (Box 9)
      People; Students; Horse sports; Athletics; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson students reading a book together, 1965; UA033.001.009.00002.00002; Unknown (Box 9)
    - Jackson swimming lesson, 1965; UA033.001.009.00002.00003; Unknown (Box 9)
  - Jackson College photographs, 1965 -- 1969; UA033.001.009.00003 (Box 9)
    - Jackson students gathered in doorway, 1969; UA033.001.009.00003.00001; Arrand, W. (Box 9)
    - Jackson students at the bursar's office, 1965; UA033.001.009.00003.00002; Taylor Publishing Co. (Box 9)
    - Jackson sit-in, 1969; UA033.001.009.00003.00003; Arrand, W. (Box 9)
      Identified on back of photo: Miss Davidson.
      People; Students; Activism; photographic print; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1965 -- 1967; UA033.001.009.00004 (Box 9)
    - Jackson students playing basketball, 1967; UA033.001.009.00004.00001; Unknown (Box 9)
      People; Students; Athletics; Basketball; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson field hockey team, 1965; UA033.001.009.00004.00002; Unknown (Box 9)
      People; Students; Athletics; Field Hockey; photographic print; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1961; UA033.001.009.00005 (Box 9)
    - Jackson students at pool, 1961; UA033.001.009.00005.00001; Unknown (Box 9)
    - Jackson students in dance class, 1961; UA033.001.009.00005.00002; Unknown (Box 9)
  - Jackson College photographs, 1962 -- 1967; UA033.001.009.00006 (Box 9)
    - Jackson students in class, 1967; UA033.001.009.00006.00001; Unknown (Box 9)
      Students; Women; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Winter carnival snow sculpture at Jackson, 1962; UA033.001.009.00006.00002; Unknown (Box 9)
      Winter Carnival; Snow; Sculpture; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson outdoor basketball game, 1967; UA033.001.009.00006.00003; Unknown (Box 9)
    - Jackson students in laboratory, 1965; UA033.001.009.00006.00004; Unknown (Box 9)
      Laboratories; Students; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Basketball players watch the hoop, 1967; UA033.001.009.00006.00005; Unknown (Box 9)
  - Jackson College photographs, 1970 -- 1976; UA033.001.009.00007 (Box 9)
    - Gwen Holden speaking in meeting at Jackson, 1970; UA033.001.009.00007.00001; Duette Photographers (Box 9)
      Identified on the back: Gwen Holden, J'70, Dean Kathryn McCarthy, J'45, G'46
      Students; Meetings; College administrators; photographic print; McCarthy, Kathryn; Jackson College
    - Mrs. Ethel Dufett, 1970; UA033.001.009.00007.00002; Duette Photographers (Box 9)
      Alumni and alumnae; photographic print; Duffett, Ethel; Jackson College
    - Dean Kathryn McCarthy speaking in meeting at Jackson, 1970; UA033.001.009.00007.00003; Duette Photographers (Box 9)
      Identified on the back, left to right: Assistant Dean Elizabeth Toupin, Deborah A. Pierce, Gwen Holden, Dean Kathryn A. McCarthy
      Students; College administrators; Meetings; photographic print; Toupin, Elizabeth; McCarthy, Kathryn; Jackson College
    - Elizabeth Toupin speaking in meeting at Jackson, 1970; UA033.001.009.00007.00004; Duette Photographers (Box 9)
      Identified on the back, left to right: Mrs. Raymond W. Eldridge (Mildred Ward, J'25), Elizabeth Toupin, Deborah A. Pierce, J'71, Gwen Holden, J'70, Dean Kathryn A. McCarthy
    - Jenny Payette playing lacrosse, 1975; UA033.001.009.00007.00005; Unknown (Box 9)
      Students; Athletics; Lacrosse; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson lacrosse match, 1975; UA033.001.009.00007.00006; Unknown (Box 9)
      Lacrosse; Athletics; Women; Students; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Jackson field hockey, 1975; UA033.001.009.00007.00007; Unknown (Box 9)
      Field Hockey; Athletics; Women; Students; photographic print; Jackson College
    - Students at Jackson continuing education graduation, 1976; UA033.001.009.00007.00008; Ellis Herwig Photography (Box 9)
      Identified on the back: Roberta Hoke, Gigliola Panico, Sally Mlervsky, Jeanne Kelley, Mary McCann, Mary-Ann Gauthier
      Students; Caps; Continuing education; photographic print; Jackson College
  - Jackson College photographs, 1980 -- 1985; UA033.001.009.00008 (Box 9)
  - Jackson College Athletic Association scrapbook, 1935 -- 1946; UA033.001.010.00001 (Box 10)
  - Jackson College Athletic Association scrapbook, 1942 -- 1948; UA033.001.010.00002 (Box 10)
  - Jackson College Athletic Association scrapbook, 1952 -- 1955; UA033.001.010.00003 (Box 10)
  - [Correspondence and reports re: admitting women to Tufts], 1871 -- 1892; UA033.001.011.00001 (Box 11)
  - [General correspondence and reports], 1893 -- 1909; UA033.001.011.00002 (Box 11)
  - [Letters to Hamilton in support of segregation], 1907 -- 1910; UA033.001.011.00003 (Box 11)
  - [Faculty and segregation], 1908 -- 1910; UA033.001.011.00004 (Box 11)
  - [Alumnae correspondence], 1909 -- 1910; UA033.001.011.00005 (Box 11)
  - [Trustee's vote], 1910; UA033.001.011.00006 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports re: Jackson College], 1910; UA033.001.011.00007 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence], 1911 -- 1912; UA033.001.011.00008 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports], 1912 -- 1929; UA033.001.011.00009 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports], 1915 -- 1917; UA033.001.011.00010 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports], 1918 -- 1919; UA033.001.011.00011 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports], 1920 -- 1925; UA033.001.011.00012 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports], 1926 -- 1930; UA033.001.011.00013 (Box 11)
  - Jackson Infirmary [Russell Miller title], 1927 -- 1946; UA033.001.011.00014 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports], 1931 -- 1936; UA033.001.011.00015 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports], 1942 -- 1945; UA033.001.011.00016 (Box 11)
  - [Correspondence and reports], 1948 -- 1976; UA033.001.011.00017 (Box 11)
  - Oversized wooden Jackson College crest, 1910; UA033.001.012.00001 (Box 12)
    Original of Jackson College designed by President Hamilton
    Jackson College
  - '30 freshman, 1926; UA033.001.013.00001 (Box Shared 127)
    A pin marked '30 is attached to the poster. Please do not place anything on top of this item since the weight of the pin will cause damage to the materials below. This item was found uncataloged in the stacks in the Spring of 2009. Note it's arrangement, it is housed in a box with other oversized materials.
    poster
  - 1932 to 1933, UA033.001.013.00002 (Box Shared 127)
    This item was found uncataloged in the stacks in the Spring of 2009. Note its location, it is housed in a box with other oversized materals.
  - Frosh of 1932!, 1928; UA033.001.013.00003 (Box Shared 127)
    This item was found uncataloged in the stacks in the Spring of 2009. Note is locations, it is housed in box with other oversized materials.
  - Traditions, Jackson '31, 1927; UA033.001.013.00004 (Box Shared 127)
    This item was found uncataloged in the stacks in the Spring of 2009. Note its locations, it is housed in a box with other oversized materials.
  - Traditions, Jackson '31, 1927; UA033.001.013.00005 (Box Shared 127)
- Additional accessions, 1955; UA033.002
  - Jackson Name Signs, Bulletin, Panty Raids, 1955; UA033-001 (Box data_value_missing_0e0cfd6df2a9f0b67c6c749715c6bcdd, Box 1)